<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-21T06:01:38+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dr. Tara Burke, NMD</title><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Long Cycle</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/the-long-cycle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Long Cycle" /><published>2020-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/the-long-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/the-long-cycle/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-long-cycle&quot;&gt;The Long Cycle&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why your cycle isn’t regular or why it is longer than “normal”? This article explores possible reasons why your cycle is long and how to find the root cause as to why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cycle-length&quot;&gt;Cycle Length&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it is important to define what a long cycle means to you. Is it regular every 2 months? Is it not the “normal” 28 days but instead every 35 days? Or is it totally unpredictable, coming every 2- 6 months? There are a few categories listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not Cycling/ No Period (Amenorrhea)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;No period ever in lifetime&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Previously cycling but period has stopped&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cycling:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Regularly Irregular (ex. cycle every 3 months- predictable)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Irregular Cycle – (ex. cycle is every 2 months or 1 month – you cannot predict when your period will arrive)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Irregular Long (ex. cycle is every 6 months, 3 months – you cannot predict when your period would arrive)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;medical-definitions-of-a-long-cycle&quot;&gt;Medical Definitions of a Long Cycle:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oligomenorrhea&lt;/strong&gt;, “a long cycle”, is defined as fewer than nine menstrual cycles per year AND/OR a cycle length greater than 35 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amenorrhea&lt;/strong&gt;, not having a period, is defined as no period for 3 months if you used to have regular cycles OR no period for a period of 6 months if you have a history of irregular cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your cycle history and frequency there are different reasons why your cycle is long. It is important to tell your doctor about the frequency and regularity of your cycle to help them narrow down a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-reasons-for-a-long-cycle&quot;&gt;Possible Reasons for a Long Cycle:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many reasons for why your cycle might be long, whether it is due to a condition, comorbid condition, or hormone imbalance. Finding the reason why your cycle is long is the most important thing to finding the best way to treat it. Here is a non-exhaustive list of some common problems that I see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endocrine Disorder or Hormone Imbalances
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autoimmune Conditions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PCOS&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tumors&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anatomical Changes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Female Hormone Imbalances&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diet
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Irregular eating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Undereating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eating disorders&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excessive Exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chronic Illness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Genetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluation&quot;&gt;Evaluation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;labs&quot;&gt;Labs:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I would order a comprehensive set of labs to look at what your hormones are doing and rule in or out other causes for a long cycle, for example, a thyroid condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic –&lt;/strong&gt; CBC, CMP, Lipids&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hormones –&lt;/strong&gt; Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, Testosterone, LH, FSH, Prolactin, DHEA-S, SHBG (It is important to note that it is preferential to have hormones tested on certain days of your cycle, this can be difficult to determine if your cycle is very irregular so it is best to talk with a healthcare professional to determine what day is best for you)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thyroid –&lt;/strong&gt; TSH, FT3, FT4, Thyroid Antibodies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pregnancy –&lt;/strong&gt; Pregnancy Test! Believe it or not sometimes, however unlikely this is, it can happen!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;imaging&quot;&gt;Imaging:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes imaging is needed beyond lab work to help determine a cause. These are some imaging options that I consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MRI of the Brain:&lt;/strong&gt; Your brain is the controller of your hormones.  This can look for any issues that could impair how your brain is talking to the rest of your body including your female reproductive system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultrasound of the Female Reproductive Organs:&lt;/strong&gt; This will provide a look at your uterus and ovaries to see if there are any anatomical issues for why your cycle is long. For example, in PCOS multiple cysts on your ovaries are often visualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;treatment&quot;&gt;Treatment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hard part because treatment totally depends on the reason why! There is no one treatment that fits all. The approach to a patient who has thyroid disease is very different from the patient who has PCOS. This is why it is important to go to a doctor who will determine the root cause of your cycle irregularity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Welt CK. Evaluation and management of secondary amenorrhea. https://www.uptodate.com/contents/evaluation-and-management-of-secondary-amenorrhea?search=olgiomenorrhea&amp;amp;source=search_result&amp;amp;selectedTitle=1~107&amp;amp;usage_type=default&amp;amp;display_rank=1. Accessed April 13, 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><summary type="html">Have you ever wondered why your cycle isn’t regular or why it is longer than “normal”? This article explores possible reasons why your cycle is long and how to find the root cause as to why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hearth Health in Thyroid Disease</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/heart-health-in-thyroid-disease/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hearth Health in Thyroid Disease" /><published>2020-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/heart-health-in-thyroid-disease</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/heart-health-in-thyroid-disease/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;hearth-health-in-thyroid-disease&quot;&gt;Hearth Health in Thyroid Disease&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I check the box for lipids on lab work, I often get a questioning look from patients. “Why are you checking my cholesterol on a thyroid panel?” At first glance it may seem unrelated but in reality, it can be very important!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-why-do-i-check-lipid-levels-often-in-thyroid-patients&quot;&gt;So, why do I check lipid levels often in thyroid patients?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your thyroid not only impacts metabolism, weight, bone health, mood, digestive function, and your menstrual cycle, but also your lipid levels – like cholesterol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clinically-i-have-seen-correlations-to-increased-lipids-levels-on-lab-work-when-a-patients-thyroid-function-is-suboptimal-why-is-this&quot;&gt;Clinically, I have seen correlations to increased lipids levels on lab work when a patient’s thyroid function is suboptimal. Why is this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your thyroid gland plays an important role in regulating cholesterol. When you are hypothyroid (your thyroid isn’t working well enough) your lipid levels, including cholesterol, often elevate.  This is because your body is not removing lipids as well as it should and bad cholesterol starts to accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it is important to note that cholesterol in our blood stream is present in two basic forms: high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and low-density lipoprotein (LDL). HDL is “good cholesterol”, it helps to reduce the amount of cholesterol in the body. LDL is “bad cholesterol” and is what will start to build up if thyroid levels are not well controlled. This is what is known to clog your arteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-sluggish-does-my-thyroid-have-to-be-for-the-changes-to-occur&quot;&gt;How sluggish does my thyroid have to be for the changes to occur?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people, even a little dip in thyroid levels can cause major impacts on your lipids. You don’t have to be way out of the normal range! And it’s not just the Thyroid hormones you have to watch but also TSH. If your TSH is elevated but your thyroid hormones are normal, your cholesterol could elevate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;now-why-is-this-important&quot;&gt;Now why is this important?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we have all heard that cholesterol is dangerous at high levels and this is very true. Elevated cholesterol can lead to cardiovascular disease. If cholesterol is not broken down properly/ it can start to form plaques in arteries and lead to obstruction of these arteries. Now most information out there about cholesterol is related to lifestyle, which is also very important, but just one piece of the puzzle in thyroid disease. Yes, you may need to take a good look at what you are eating but for many of my patients this is not always the case. They have outstanding diets, exercise regularly but come to see me with elevated cholesterol levels. If these patients are also experiencing hypothyroid symptoms this may be an important factor to consider. All in all, if you have high cholesterol, you should be screened for hypothyroidism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ross DS. Lipid abnormalities in thyroid disease. https://www.uptodate.com/contents/lipid-abnormalities-in-thyroid-disease?search=thyroid%20cholesterol&amp;amp;source=search_result&amp;amp;selectedTitle=1~150&amp;amp;usage_type=default&amp;amp;display_rank=1. Accessed April 13, 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><category term="Thyroid" /><summary type="html">Your thyroid not only impacts metabolism, weight, bone health, mood, digestive function, and your menstrual cycle, but also your lipid levels – like cholesterol.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hormones In PCOS</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/hormones-in-pcos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hormones In PCOS" /><published>2020-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/hormones-in-pcos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/hormones-in-pcos/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;hormones-in-pcos&quot;&gt;Hormones in PCOS&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women have reached out to ask me to explain what their hormones look like if they have PCOS and this is a great follow up after looking at “normal cycles” and hormones for those on “the pill”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCOS is a hormonal disorder which is commonly diagnosed in young women. It was named for multiple cysts seen on the ovaries of patients diagnosed with PCOS, although this is a bit of a misnomer as patients with PCOS will not always have cystic ovaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;symptoms-of-pcos&quot;&gt;Symptoms of PCOS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular periods or absence of your period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unusual or unwanted hair growth, for example hair growth on the chin or head hair loss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acne&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High blood sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High blood pressure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight gain or the inability to lose weight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inability to get pregnant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fatigue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hormones&quot;&gt;Hormones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the last two posts, it is much harder to provide a diagram of what hormones will look like in a cycle. This is because PCOS can present differently in various patients. Some people may have a 2-month cycle, some may not ovulate, and some may cycle regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple female hormones that PCOS will affect like androgens, estrogen, and progesterone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;androgens&quot;&gt;Androgens:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All females normally produce small amounts of androgens, like testosterone. In PCOS patients these androgens are usually greatly elevated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;estrogen&quot;&gt;Estrogen:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common clinical patterns I see in PCOS patients is estrogen dominance. This happens when your estrogen levels are too high relative to progesterone levels. If you need a refresher on what estrogen dominance is click here. There are three forms of estrogen in our body- Estradiol (E2), Estrone (E1), and Estriol (E3). Premenopausal Estradiol should be the dominant form of estrogen. Postmenopausal Estrone takes over as the dominant from of estrogen and in pregnancy Estriol is dominant. In PCOS patients, I often see Estrone levels higher then Estradiol, this is problematic for these patients and can impact symptoms and fertility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;progesterone&quot;&gt;Progesterone:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progesterone levels are often decreased in PCOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lh-and-fsh&quot;&gt;LH and FSH:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LH and FSH are also hormones involved in a women’s menstrual cycle. In a “normal” female the ratio of LH to FSH is 1:1 (except right before ovulation) but in PCOS this ratio will often be abnormal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-is-pcos-diagnosed&quot;&gt;How is PCOS diagnosed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the most widely accepted way is by using something called the Rotterdam criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of three are needed to make the diagnosis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oligo – and/or anovulation – which means irregular cycles or you are not ovulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical and/or biochemical signs of hyperandrogenism – which means signs of high testosterone like acne or unwanted hair growth (like on the chin) OR high androgen on your labs work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Polycystic ovaries (by ultrasound) – exactly like it sounds, cysts are seen on your ovaries when imaging is performed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><category term="PCOS" /><summary type="html">PCOS is a hormonal disorder which is commonly diagnosed in young women. It was named for multiple cysts seen on the ovaries of patients diagnosed with PCOS, although this is a bit of a misnomer as patients with PCOS will not always have cystic ovaries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Do My Hormones Look Like On “The Pill”?</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/what-do-my-hormones-look-like-on-the-pill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Do My Hormones Look Like On “The Pill”?" /><published>2020-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/what-do-my-hormones-look-like-on-the-pill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/what-do-my-hormones-look-like-on-the-pill/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-do-my-hormones-look-like-on-the-pill&quot;&gt;What do my Hormones look like on “The Pill”?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous blog post, we discussed what a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://drtaraburke.com/what-is-a-normal-cycle/&quot;&gt;normal cycle&lt;/a&gt;” should look like and what your hormone levels should be. But what happens to your cycle when you are on a combination birth control pill? Today’s article will look at how the pill changes your hormones and cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most birth control pills contain two of the female hormones, estrogen and progesterone. These are termed combination pills. By taking the pill every day, the high levels of synthetic estrogen and progesterone make your body think that you are already pregnant.  This stops ovulation from occurring – you don’t release a viable egg and therefore it cannot be fertilized to cause a pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hormonal birth control is very effective at preventing pregnancy and for many women, this is a great option for their health goals and needs. For other women, roughly half of those who have tried hormonal birth control, it can come with many unwanted side effects like nausea, boating, breast tenderness, fatigue, sleep issues, and emotional changes. It is no surprise why many women decide to discontinue hormonal birth control due to the side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your blood hormone levels look vastly different when you take the pill versus when you are cycling naturally. If you need a refresher on how your hormones cycle during the course of the month, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://drtaraburke.com/what-is-a-normal-cycle/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The high levels of estrogen and progesterone also influence LH and FSH, which usually rise dramatically to trigger ovulation. When you are taking the pill, the high levels of synthetic progesterone and estrogen keep LH and FSH low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are familiar with the pill, you will recall that a birth control pack consists of 21 hormone pills and seven placebo pills. You take 21 hormone pills in a row for three weeks, then take the seven placebo pills for one week. The placebo pills are really nothing but sugar and only function to help women keep track of how long they should take a break from the hormone containing pills. The sudden withdrawal of the hormones on this break triggers a “period”. This is not really a true period – it is actually withdrawal bleeding due to the discontinuation of the hormones and is why “periods” on the pill are usually much lighter and less painful for many women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to answer the original question, estrogen and progestin remain at predictable high levels during days 1-21 but this is a reflection of the synthetic hormones from the pill. When you take the “sugar pills” for seven days, hormone levels plummet and you have withdrawal bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bit of a simplification, in reality synthetic hormone levels fluctuate during the day. They peak when you take the pill and decrease over the next few hours until you have taken another pill, but on average they stay elevated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estrogen and progesterone levels are a reflection largely of the synthetic hormones in your system and not endogenous levels, the hormones you produce yourself. Usually women on the pill will have low levels of endogenous estrogen and progesterone, but that does not mean they do not experience hormonal type symptoms from the synthetic hormones.When doctors draw hormone labs while you are on the pill, it can be informative but not always useful. Labs can validate and confirm the symptoms you may be experiencing, but that is pretty predictable without labs as well.  Here is the real catch, if you are experiencing symptoms on the pill there is only so much you can do without affecting the efficacy of your birth control. It is important to remember that there are many different types of hormonal and non-hormonal birth control that work differently than the combination pill discussed above. If you are unhappy with your current birth control or are looking for a non-hormonal method make sure you talk to your doctor!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><summary type="html">Most birth control pills contain two of the female hormones, estrogen and progesterone. These are termed combination pills. By taking the pill every day, the high levels of synthetic estrogen and progesterone make your body think that you are already pregnant. This stops ovulation from</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is a Normal Cycle?</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/what-is-a-normal-cycle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a Normal Cycle?" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/what-is-a-normal-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/what-is-a-normal-cycle/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-normal-cycle&quot;&gt;What is a Normal Cycle?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often find myself talking to my patients about abnormal cycles – whether that be the length of their period/cycle, the amount of flow, clotting, pain, etc. I thought that I would go back to some basics this week to write about what a normal cycle should look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical cycle comes every 25-30 days, menses is 5-7 days. As far as flow is concerned, you should not have to change more than a pad or super tampon every hour for three or more consecutive hours in one day. Initially, your blood should appear similar to a bright red in color and can then fade to a brownish color as your period ends. PMS and cramping should be minimal and you should not experience pain during your period. Even a “normal” cycle varies from person to person. The moral of the story is that a cycle should not be too long or short and should not affect your daily life. If your cycle is impacting your lifestyle then chances are you have an abnormal cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hormones&quot;&gt;Hormones:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok let’s talk hormones, female hormones. What are they and how do they change over the course of the month? Here’s the breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main hormone players in females are Estrogen, Progesterone, Luteinizing Hormone (LH), Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH), and Testosterone. Depending where you are in your cycle, the levels are different. LH and FSH are produced in your brain and travel down to your ovaries to trigger ovulation. Estrogen Progesterone are produced in your ovaries where they function to prepare your uterus for pregnancy by producing and maintaining your uterine lining, making it a cozy environment for a fertilized egg.  How these hormones work together is easier to show visually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/TheCycle.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Cycle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cycle&quot;&gt;The Cycle:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your cycle is broken down into 2 main phases – the &lt;strong&gt;Follicular Phase&lt;/strong&gt;, which is from day 1 to 14, and the &lt;strong&gt;Luteal Phase&lt;/strong&gt;, which is day 14-28. As you can see, your &lt;strong&gt;Period&lt;/strong&gt; starts on day 1 of your cycle which is in the &lt;strong&gt;Follicular Phase&lt;/strong&gt;. At the start of the follicular phase, your estrogen, progesterone, FSH, and LH levels are low. As we move into the next few days of the cycle, your &lt;strong&gt;Period&lt;/strong&gt; will end, typically around day 5-6. Leading up to day 14, which is when &lt;strong&gt;Ovulation&lt;/strong&gt; occurs, your estrogen levels start to increase. This is what is getting your uterus ready for &lt;strong&gt;ovulation&lt;/strong&gt;. Right before Day 14, LH and FSH spike; triggering &lt;strong&gt;Ovulation&lt;/strong&gt;! &lt;strong&gt;Ovulation&lt;/strong&gt; is the time in a woman’s cycle that an egg is released. The &lt;strong&gt;Luteal Phase&lt;/strong&gt; begins after &lt;strong&gt;Ovulation&lt;/strong&gt; and is when estrogen levels rise. This function of this rise in estrogen is to prepare the uterus for pregnancy. Your progesterone levels also begin to rise dramatically and peak during day 21 of your cycle. This prepares the uterus, by building the uterine lining for implantation of the egg if it is fertilized by sperm during the magic window in your cycle. If the egg implants into the uterus, this is a pregnancy and estrogen and progesterone levels will remain high to maintain the pregnancy. If the egg is not fertilized, your levels of estrogen and progesterone decrease and the uterine lining is shed, AKA your period and the cycle begins anew!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><summary type="html">I often find myself talking to my patients about abnormal cycles – whether that be the length of their period/cycle, the amount of flow, clotting, pain, etc. I thought that I would go back to some</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Top Health Concerns In Busy Moms</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/top-health-concerns-in-busy-moms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Top Health Concerns In Busy Moms" /><published>2020-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/top-health-concerns-in-busy-moms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/top-health-concerns-in-busy-moms/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;top-health-concerns-in-busy-moms&quot;&gt;Top Health Concerns in Busy Moms&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of speaking to a group of mom entrepreneurs this past week about the Top Health Concerns I see in Busy Moms. For all of you that were not able to attend, I thought I would give a summary blog post of the highlights!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thyroid-health&quot;&gt;Thyroid Health:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your thyroid is a butterfly shaped gland that sits at the base of your neck. It is a small but mighty gland that helps with metabolism, weight, control, heart health, bone health, regulating your menstrual cycle, temperature, mood, digestive health, and your energy. Yes, it really does it all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different kinds and causes of thyroid conditions. Hashimoto’s, which is an autoimmune condition of the thyroid, is one of the most common conditions I see and treat in my practice.  Why? A few reasons… Hashimoto’s is more likely to happen in women than men, your risk is higher after pregnancy or after a stressful event.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Autoimmune thyroid disease is due to environmental factor but also tends to run in families.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symptoms of thyroid disease are often missed or dismissed in mothers. A lot of the symptoms of thyroid disease can be blamed on a busy lifestyle, pregnancy, breastfeeding, stress etc. AKA “you are just too busy and that’s why you are tired all the time”, “hair loss is normal for new moms,” “you are working and raising kids, are you sure you are exercising enough?”, “you are just stressed”. But a lot of the time, it’s not just lifestyle to blame! Having thyroid disease and juggling work-life balance is like pushing a boulder uphill! I have to say the most common cause of fatigue in busy moms I see in my practice is a sluggish thyroid. There are many symptoms of thyroid disease so please download my &lt;a href=&quot;../assets/handouts/Thyroid-signs-and-symptoms-1.xls&quot;&gt;list of common symptoms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stress of pregnancy, hormonal changes, and a busy life can all contribute to your thyroid health. Just checking your thyroid hormones is a simple balance to start. With my patients I start with TSH, FT3. FT4, and Thyroid antibodies. Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://drtaraburke.com/thyroid-testing/&quot;&gt;thyroid testing&lt;/a&gt;. Imaging, like a thyroid ultrasound, can be a good idea if there is a family history of thyroid disease or a personal history of elevated antibodies. If your provider feels any sort of changes or abnormalities on an examination of your thyroid, then  imaging would also be indicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adrenal-health&quot;&gt;Adrenal Health:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your adrenal glands are located above your kidneys and help with your stress response. Cortisol is released from your adrenals and regulates your energy levels over the course of the day and night. Too little cortisol output equals fatigue and too much cortisol can cause anxiety during the day and insomnia at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a busy mom, or anyone that has a busy lifestyle, can worsen daily stress levels which in turn strains your adrenal glands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/normal-cortisol.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Normal Cortisol&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a wide variety of dysfunctional patterns that all cause a variety of symptoms and thus need a different treatment approach. There is no one pill, herb, or supplement that is good for all types of adrenal dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;female-hormone-health&quot;&gt;Female Hormone Health:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various types of hormone imbalances. Your environment, lifestyle, and genetics play a role on how your hormone levels change in your teens, pregnancy, and into motherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this there is no one treatment that fits all. For conditions like PCOS, endometriosis, and perimenopause, surgery and medications like the pill are not your only options, there are many natural and effective options available as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common pattern of hormonal imbalance I see in busy moms is elevated estrogen, also known as estrogen dominance. Other patterns of hormonal imbalance include decreased levels of estrogen, elevated testosterone, and low testosterone. The most important thing is that estrogen and progesterone are balanced relative to each other and there is an appropriate amount of testosterone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Davies, T. F. Pathogenesis of Hashimoto’s thyroiditis (chronic autoimmune thyroiditis). Up to Date (2020). Available at: https://www.uptodate.com/contents/pathogenesis-of-hashimotos-thyroiditis-chronic-autoimmune-thyroiditis?search=hashimotos&amp;amp;source=search_result&amp;amp;selectedTitle=1~122&amp;amp;usage_type=default&amp;amp;display_rank=1. (Accessed: 18th January 2020) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Motherhood" /><summary type="html">Your thyroid is a butterfly shaped gland that sits at the base of your neck. It is a small but mighty gland that helps with metabolism, weight, control, heart health, bone health, regulating</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supplements to Balance Hormones</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/supplements-to-balance-hormones/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supplements to Balance Hormones" /><published>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/supplements-to-balance-hormones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/supplements-to-balance-hormones/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;supplements-to-balance-hormones&quot;&gt;Supplements to Balance Hormones&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hormone balance is one of the most common reasons patients pay me an initial visit, and a common question is whether I recommend supplements to balance hormones. In recent years, focus on women’s health has gone from just a yearly PAP smear and breast exam to discussion around optimal health and wellness. Women feel empowered to talk to their health care providers about topics that were previously perceived as “normal”- things like painful periods and PMS symptoms which includes cravings, mood changes, acne, and changes during perimenopause. Seeking treatment for hormone balance means that women are finally able to start the journey to optimal health and complete wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I would take some time to discuss some of my favorite herbs, nutrients, and nutrition options for hormone balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, choosing supplements for hormone balance isn’t always cut and dry. Depending on why your hormones are imbalanced can mean that is it time for a different treatment plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;types-of-hormone-imbalances&quot;&gt;Types of Hormone Imbalances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estrogen Dominance – &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hormone.org/your-health-and-hormones/glands-and-hormones-a-to-z/hormones/estrogen&quot;&gt;Estrogen&lt;/a&gt; dominance is a quite common cause of hormone imbalance that occurs when estrogen levels are too high relative to progesterone levels. This can happen in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevated estrogen levels:&lt;/strong&gt; Estrogen levels can become elevated due to environmental exposures, medications, poor hormone metabolism, or ovarian cysts/tumors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depressed progesterone levels:&lt;/strong&gt; Progesterone levels may depress due to various conditions such as Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS), menopause, or hypothyroidism.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combination:&lt;/strong&gt; Any pattern in between the that causes higher estrogen relative to progesterone can also result in estrogen dominance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symptoms of estrogen dominance include: Tender breasts, irregular cycles – long or short, bloating, acne, breast cysts, PMS, headaches, anxiety, weight gain, difficulty sleeping, fatigue, hair loss, and difficulties getting pregnant. However, this is not an all-inclusive list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/img/Copy-of-Est-Dom-Patterns-Graphic.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Supplements To Balance Hormones Chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graphic above shows a healthy pattern and 3 patterns of estrogen dominance. Please take note that all of the unhealthy patterns are still within a typical lab reference range. Your hormones will come back “normal”. It’s the ratio between the hormones that are important! Adding a healthy pattern to the previously mentioned reasons for Estrogen Dominance leaves us with the following patterns for your hormones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Healthy Pattern:&lt;/strong&gt; Levels of Estrogen and Progesterone are at optimal levels. Estrogen and Progesterone are balanced&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevated Estrogen:&lt;/strong&gt; Estrogen levels have increased past optimal levels while progesterone has stayed the same. Estrogen and Progesterone are unbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depressed Progesterone:&lt;/strong&gt; Estrogen levels are at an optimal level while progesterone has stays decreased. Estrogen and Progesterone are unbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combination:&lt;/strong&gt; Estrogen and progesterone are out of optimal ranges. Estrogen and Progesterone are unbalanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low Estrogen –&lt;/strong&gt; this is very characteristic for peri and post-menopausal women. As women transition into menopause, infrequent or nonexistent periods mean decreasing estrogen levels. For some women this transition is mild while for others it is very severe and debilitating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signs and symptoms include hot flashes, night sweats, vaginal dryness, joint and muscle pain, brain fog, bone loss, and low sex drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevated Progesterone –&lt;/strong&gt; While not as common as estrogen dominance, this hormonal imbalance is still possible. Elevated Progesterone most often results from inappropriately dosed hormone replacement therapy. It can also occur with certain congenital disorders, ovarian cysts, and tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symptoms of progesterone dominance are very sensitive to the cause but can include, bloating, sleepiness and grogginess, and mood changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevated Testosterone –&lt;/strong&gt; This is commonly seen in disorders like Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS), hirsutism, inappropriate dosed hormone replacement therapy, or less common congenital syndromes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signs of Elevated Testosterone include acne, unwanted/inappropriate hair growth on places such as your chin, irregular periods, and feeling “more aggressive/irritated”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low Testosterone –&lt;/strong&gt; Low &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hormone.org/your-health-and-hormones/glands-and-hormones-a-to-z/hormones/testosterone&quot;&gt;Testosterone&lt;/a&gt; is also seen commonly in the peri and post-menopause stages and is unfortunately a common part of ageing. I am also seeing it more frequently in younger females and can be an indicator of issues in the ovaries or adrenal glands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signs of Low Testosterone include low libido, fatigue, weakness, and depressed mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other hormone imbalances –&lt;/strong&gt; Thyroid and adrenal health can be impacted by changes in female hormone health. Conversely, female hormone health can be impacted by disorders of thyroid and adrenal glands. The best way to determine diagnosis and treatment is to see your health care provider that is trained in hormone imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;herbs-nutrients-and-nutrition-options-for-hormone-balance&quot;&gt;Herbs, Nutrients, and Nutrition Options for Hormone Balance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Naturopathic Physician, I am lucky to have so many “tools in my toolbox” to provide treatment options to my patients having hormonal balance issues! Depending on symptom severity and patient preference, I can choose between a variety of options that will work best for them. This is one of the many reasons that I love Naturopathic Medicine and one of the reasons I often use supplements to balance hormones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;herbal-and-alternative-medicine&quot;&gt;Herbal and Alternative Medicine:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love using herbal formulations with my patients in order to provide safe and effective relief for their symptoms. Herbals are a gentle way to treat for many symptoms such as hot flashes, painful periods, unpredictable periods, hormonal acne, fertility, sleep, and more! Here are some common herbal supplements to balance hormones and combat these unwanted issues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Black Cohosh (Cimicifuga or Actaea racemose):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This herb is very famous for its use in menopause, especially for hot flashes. There have been mixed results from research studies on the efficacy of this herb but clinically it has been effective for many patients. I personally find it to be a good option when used in conjunction with other herbals in a formula for menopause. Overshadowed by its attention for menopause relief, this herb is also great for PMS, period cramping, and irregular periods. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaste Tree (Vitex annus):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Used traditionally for many years, Chaste Tree Berry is a very famous herb in the realm of hormone balance! It works on the pituitary gland to increase the luteinizing hormone (LH), stimulating ovulation and increasing progesterone.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is often used to provide relief from PMS symptoms. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is a great choice for depressed progesterone levels and/or elevated estrogen levels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kava (Piper methysticum):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is a personal favorite herb of mine! Why? Because it does so much, it is one of the best herbal supplements to balance hormones! It is noted for its calming but non-sedative effects&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and efficacy for menopausal symptoms. It also effective at alleviating painful periods due to its muscle relaxant properties.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maca (Lepidium Peruvianum):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is another personal favorite of mine. It is wonderful for women in all stages of life – from helping regulate cycles in young women to relieving menopausal symptoms. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fenugreek:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This herb is most widely known for its use to encourage milk production in breastfeeding mothers. One of its lesser known abilities is to help women with low testosterone level and improving libido. Although the research is still out on whether it results in a direct increase to testosterone, it consistently seems to have a positive effect on the libido. It is also indicated for helping with insulin sensitivity, which is a common use case in patients with Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS). &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Licorice and Saw palmetto:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; These herbs are a great choice for those looking to lower testosterone levels such as in patients with Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS). &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dandelion Root and Burdock:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; No discussion about hormone balance and herbs would be complete without talking about these herbs due to their liver loving affinities. You may be wondering why would you need liver herbs for hormone balance? Well, because many of our hormones are metabolized and broken down in our liver. Promoting healthy metabolism means toxins and excess hormone products don’t build up! Dandelion Root &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Burdock &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are two such herbs, and that makes them great supplements to balance hormones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diindolymethyl (DIM):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This amazing supplement comes from cruciferous vegetables. It is most often indicated for cases with elevated estrogen. This is due to the fact that it promotes favorable metabolism of estrogen. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there are so many wonderful herbal supplements to balance hormones that I cannot possibly mention them all. It is also important to know that there is more to herbs that simply checking what health issues they are indicated for. They also have synergistic properties, which means that some herbs work better together! A naturopathic doctor can come up with a herbal formula that is dosed safely and appropriately for your individualized health history and concerns. There are also pre-made supplements on the market which are formulated for hormone balance. My trustworthy brands in this category include Vitanica and Femenessence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nutrition&quot;&gt;Nutrition:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often times we can’t rely solely on herbal supplements to balance hormones, and thus we must combine it with another method. One of my favorite ways to compliment herbal therapies is with dietary recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cruciferous Veggies:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; For estrogen dominant conditions, cruciferous vegetables are a wonderful way to help metabolize estrogens better as the contain Indole-3-carbinol (I3C), which favors the less active form of estrogen. 2 Vegetables in general can help enhance liver function which is important since estrogen metabolites can build up if your liver isn’t working optimally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flax seed:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Known as a superfood, Flax Seed is also a wonderful addition to your diet to help with estrogen levels, as it acts as a phytoestrogen. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; What is a phytoestrogen? It is a component that acts like estrogen in the body. This mean it can help with high or low estrogen levels. How? Because it works in the body on estrogen receptors, allowing it to regulate hormone levels appropriately, becoming weakly estrogenic or antiestrogenic. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In this way it can help regulate menstrual cycles and is great for elevated or depressed estrogen levels. It can also help to bind up extra androgens, like testosterone if levels are too high (like in PCOS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spearmint Tea:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is wonderful for patients who are having health issues like Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS), who are looking to help decrease testosterone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avoiding Sugar and Caffeine:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; When estrogen levels are elevated, caffeine and sugar can worsen symptoms. Thus, it is important to avoid drinks that contain these elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether a diet plan based around these changes is appropriate for you can be best determined by your health care provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bioidentical-hormone-replacement-therapy-bhrt&quot;&gt;Bioidentical Hormone Replacement Therapy (BHRT):&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my women who have more severe symptoms supplements to balance hormones may not be enough and in this case Bioidentical Hormone Replacement Therapy (BHRT) can be a great option. With proper labs, follow-up, and customized dosing, this can be a safe step up in a patient’s therapy from more natural treatments. Remember, it’s all about safety first, so using the lowest level of therapy to provide adequate symptom relief is ideal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no one herb, nutritional plan, product, or therapy that is good for everything hormones related. It is vital to determine what type of hormone imbalance you have and why. Finding the root cause to your health issues can bring you back to long-lasting optimal health – herbals, nutrition, and medications can help you there. A qualified health care professional can offer testing, interpretation, diagnosis, and treatment for your unique needs and goals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-can-you-do-now&quot;&gt;So, what can you do now?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have your period: Start tracking your menstrual cycle with all symptoms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Clean Up” your environment – be mindful of what is in your personal care products, stop microwaving and storing foods in plastic, switch to a glass or metal water bottle, and avoid processed foods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make an appointment with a skilled practitioner who is familiar with hormonal imbalance, like a naturopathic doctor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your hormone labs completed and read by your naturopathic doctor or licensed functional medicine practitioner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a look at your diet – make a diet diary of all the foods you are having for a week and bring it into your naturopathic doctor so they can help to tell you what foods are helping or hindering your hormones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make an appointment with a doctor who can help to determine what medications or supplements to balance hormones are appropriate for your type of hormone imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hudson, T. Women’s Encyclopedia of Natural Medicine [Paperback]. (McGraw-Hill; 1 edition, 1999). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hudson, T. Women’s Encyclopedia of Natural Medicine. (McGraw-Hill Education, 2007). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Brown, D. Vitex agnus castus clinical monograph. Alternative Medicine Review 14, (2009). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Schellenberg, R. Treatment for the premenstrual syndrome with agnus castus fruit extract: prospective, randomised, placebo controlled study. BMJ 322, 134–7 (2001). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Skidmore-Roth, L. Mosby’s Handbook of Herbs and Natural Supplements. (Mosby Elsevier, 2010). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gonzales, G. et al. Effect of Lepidium meyenii (Maca), a root with aphrodisiac and fertility-enhancing properties, on serum reproductive hormone levels in adult healthy men. J. Endocrinol. 176, 163–168 (2003). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Meissner, H. O., Kapczynski, W., Mscisz, A. &amp;amp; Lutomski, J. Use of gelatinized maca (lepidium peruvianum) in early postmenopausal women. Int. J. Biomed. Sci. 1, 33–45 (2005). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Murray, M. &amp;amp; Pizzorno, J. Textbook of Natural Medicine 4e. Textbook of Natural Medicine (2012). doi:10.1016/B978-1-4377-2333-5.00204-2 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><category term="Hormones" /><summary type="html">Hormone balance is one of the most common reasons patients pay me an initial visit, and a common question is whether I recommend supplements to balance hormones. In recent years, focus on women’s health has gone from just a yearly PAP smear and breast exam to discussion around optimal health</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Herbs for Hypothyroid</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/herbs-for-hypothyroid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Herbs for Hypothyroid" /><published>2019-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/herbs-for-hypothyroid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/herbs-for-hypothyroid/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;herbs-for-hypothyroid&quot;&gt;Herbs for Hypothyroid&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basics&quot;&gt;Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of benefits, drawbacks, and common misconceptions when it comes treatment using herbs for hypothyroid, so let’s lay out the facts on some of the most common ones. Firstly, hypothyroidism is a condition where your thyroid is not making enough thyroid hormone. There are various causes of hypothyroid like autoimmune conditions, diet, medications, environmental exposures, and surgical removal of the thyroid. Here are a few herbals that have been traditionally used for hypothyroidism. If you think maybe you need a refresher on how your thyroid talks to the rest of your body, go ahead and watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oo3oTNJ0DT0&quot;&gt;this quick video&lt;/a&gt; first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-most-commonly-prescribed-herb-for-hypothyroid&quot;&gt;The Most Commonly Prescribed Herb for Hypothyroid:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fucus vesiculosus, alternatively known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-726/bladderwrack&quot;&gt;Bladderwrack&lt;/a&gt;, is the herb most commonly associated with the treatment of hypothyroid. This is a kelp and seaweed product that is often used in hypothyroidism due to the high iodine content. Insufficient levels of iodine can cause hypothyroidism – BUT taking additional iodine from Bladderwrack can more often than not be detrimental to your thyroid.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Why? Iodine has a very narrow therapeutic index, meaning it has a very narrow window between an effective dose and one which produces adverse effects. Put simply, too much, or too little iodine can be harmful.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In a standard American diet most people already get plenty of iodine, meaning additional sources in supplemental or herbal form can do more harm than good. Please consult with a knowledgeable practitioner before you start taking Bladderwrack to determine if it is actually indicated in your case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; More often than not, Bladderwrack will actually provide TOO MUCH iodine and be detrimental to your system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-commonly-prescribed-herbs-for-hypothyroid&quot;&gt;Other Commonly Prescribed Herbs for Hypothyroid:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centella asiatica, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-753/gotu-kola&quot;&gt;Gotu kola&lt;/a&gt;, is a great adaptogenic herb that supports brain health, nerves, and mood.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is considered one of the safer adaptogenic herbs and is generally well tolerated by patients. One of the most common subjective symptoms that hypothyroid patients  report is “brain fog”. Centella in herbal formula can help support cognitive function. However, on its own, this herbal is not sufficient to treat hypothyroidism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This herb can help with the “brain fog” feeling you may have from hypothyroidism, but has not yet been shown by research to improve thyroid lab markers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ganoderma lucidum, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-905/reishi-mushroom&quot;&gt;mushroom&lt;/a&gt;, is an adaptogenic herb that is commonly seen in hypothyroid formulas. It improves cardiovascular health, helping reduce cholesterol which is commonly elevated in poorly controlled hypothyroidism.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Once again though, this herb has not been shown to improve thyroid function through research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This fungal herb can improve cardiovascular health and reduce cholesterol,  but has also not yet been shown by research to improve thyroid lab markers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cordyceps sinensis, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-602/cordyceps&quot;&gt;fungus&lt;/a&gt;, is also often found in hypothyroid formulas. It is a wonderful adaptogenic herbal choice for patients that are extremely fatigued. With the additional bonus that it can help with insulin sensitivity and cardiovascular health. However, once again, this herb has not been shown to improve thyroid function directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This fungus can help with fatigue, insulin sensitivity and cardiovascular health, but has also not yet been shown by research to improve thyroid lab markers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glycyrrhiza glabra, better known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-881/licorice&quot;&gt;licorice&lt;/a&gt;, is an all-around great herb. While not specifically for thyroid health, it is indicated for improving cortisol levels. Often, when the thyroid is stressed it can impact other endocrine systems like the adrenal glands, which produce cortisol. If you are feeling persistent fatigue after hypothyroid treatment, this can be due to struggling adrenals. Similarly to Centella, licorice may have some cognitive enhancing effects.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Licorice is an incredible herb that can help with improving cortisol levels and reducing fatigue, but has also not yet been shown by research to directly treat hypothyroidism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigella Sativa, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/vitamins/ai/ingredientmono-901/black-seed&quot;&gt;black cumin&lt;/a&gt;, is used in autoimmune conditions like Hashimotos. It can help decrease elevated antibody levels seen on labs. It has also been reported to help decrease TSH levels and raise T3 levels, in addition to helping to reduce weight gain often seen in hypothyroid patients.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Unlike the previous herbs, this is generally prescribed in a capsule instead of as a tincture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE BOTTOM LINE:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Black cumin is an excellent herb for autoimmune hypothyroid conditions that helps with inflammation, weight gain, and TSH/T3 levels from labs. Black cumin is a great start to treating your hypothyroid condition, but is likely not enough on it’s own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember that just because something is natural does not necessarily make it safe! Many herbals can have serious side effects, adverse reactions, interactions with other medications/supplements/herbs and may not be OK to take during pregnancy or while breastfeeding. ALWAYS ask your doctor before starting anything new.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-this-is-not-the-end-of-the-story&quot;&gt;But this is not the end of the story….&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all of these herbs have traditionally been used in hypothyroid, they are typically not enough. Serious long-term effects can result from attempting to treat your hypothyroid condition with herbals alone. Negative effects from not properly treating hypoythroid conditions include elevations in cholesterol and lipids, &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  decreased fertility,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  and  poor gastrointestinal health. Elevations in TSH can promote unwanted growth of the thyroid gland which is exceedingly important to take into consideration for patients with a history of nodules or thyroid cancer.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Regular thyroid labs and imaging completed by your healthcare professional are important for the diagnosis and management of hypothyroidism. For more info on how to test your thyroid please check out this article about &lt;a href=&quot;https://drtaraburke.com/thyroid-testing/&quot;&gt;which labs should be run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also critical to find the root cause of your hypothyroid before starting any natural treatments. Depending on the cause of your sluggish thyroid, herbal products may not be indicated and could cause more harm. Talking with your doctor before starting natural treatments is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-if-herbals-are-not-enough-on-their-own-what-are-my-other-options&quot;&gt;So, if herbals are not enough on their own what are my other options?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well this is when medications are indicated and imperative. There are various medication options to treat hypothyroidism, both synthetic and natural. Talking with your doctor to find the right type and dose of medication can help you feel better as well as mitigate complications from untreated hypothyroidism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally used herbs for hypothyroid are often not sufficient to treat hypothyroidism on their own. They are a great option to be used in conjunction with medications and dietary changes. It can help make you feel better by relieving symptoms like fatigue, weight gain, and stress, and in addition decrease elevated thyroid antibodies seen in autoimmune hypothyroid conditions. Before deciding on a treatment option or change to your treatment plan, please speak to your doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturopathic doctors have the knowledge to customize herbal prescriptions that are tailored to your unique health concerns and can safely be used with many medications. Naturopathic doctors also can help with choosing a thyroid medication that fits your unique goals and situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been diagnosed with hypothyroidism or Hashimotos, or think you may have hypothyroid I am here to answer questions and help get you back to feeling well again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Leung AM, Braverman LE. Consequences of excess iodine. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2014;10(3):136-142. doi:10.1038/nrendo.2013.251 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;WOLFF J, CHAIKOFF IL. The inhibitory action of excessive iodide upon the synthesis of diiodotyrosine and of thyroxine in the thyroid gland of the normal rat. Endocrinology. 1948;43(3):174-179. doi:10.1210/endo-43-3-174 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Murray M, Pizzorno J. Textbook of Natural Medicine 4e.; 2012. doi:10.1016/B978-1-4377-2333-5.00204-2 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hajjaj H, Macé C, Roberts M, Niederberger P, Fay LB. Effect of 26-oxygenosterols from Ganoderma lucidum and their activity as cholesterol synthesis inhibitors. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2005;71(7):3653-3658. doi:10.1128/AEM.71.7.3653-3658.2005 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Farhangi MA, Dehghan P, Tajmiri S, Abbasi MM. The effects of Nigella sativa on thyroid function , serum Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor ( VEGF ) – 1 , Nesfatin-1 and anthropometric features in patients with Hashimoto ’ s thyroiditis : a randomized controlled trial. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2016:1-9. doi:10.1186/s12906-016-1432-2 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rizos C V, Elisaf MS, Liberopoulos EN. Effects of thyroid dysfunction on lipid profile. Open Cardiovasc Med J. 2011;5:76-84. doi:10.2174/1874192401105010076 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jokar TO, Fourman LT, Lee H, Mentzinger K, Fazeli PK. Higher TSH levels within the normal range are associated with unexplained infertility. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2018;103(2):632-639. doi:10.1210/jc.2017-02120 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Haugen BR, Alexander EK, Bible KC, et al. 2015 American Thyroid Association Management Guidelines for Adult Patients with Thyroid Nodules and Differentiated Thyroid Cancer: The American Thyroid Association Guidelines Task Force on Thyroid Nodules and Differentiated Thyroid Cancer. Thyroid. 2016;26(1):1-133. doi:10.1089/thy.2015.0020 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><category term="Hypothyroid" /><summary type="html">There are a number of benefits, drawbacks, and common misconceptions when it comes treatment using herbs for hypothyroid, so let’s lay out the facts on some of the most common ones. Firstly,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toxin-Free Choices For Babies</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/toxin-free-choices-for-babies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toxin-Free Choices For Babies" /><published>2019-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/toxin-free-choices-for-babies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/toxin-free-choices-for-babies/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;toxin-free-choice-for-babies&quot;&gt;Toxin-Free Choice For Babies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding plastics is not only good for the environment, but also good for your health! While I realize one person avoiding single use plastic products won’t save the world, I am a firm believer that every little bit helps. Making these small changes in our home has become especially important because of Lil B – we want to leave this plant a better place for him!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the environmental aspects of plastic, plastics are also associated with a host of health issues. I tried to avoid all plastics in Lil B’s first year of life and continue to limit them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-some-tips&quot;&gt;Here are some Tips:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breastmilk-and-formula&quot;&gt;Breastmilk and Formula:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breastfeeding helped to avoid bottles for the most part, but when I went back to work I needed to store and pack breastmilk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use glass bottles, we loved ours from lifefactory and he hasn’t managed to break one yet!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider using glass to store breast milk in the fridge and freezer, eventually I didn’t have enough room and choose to use BPA free store bags.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When your baby is old enough for water and non-breast milks try a metal container, they are hard to break and their beverage won’t be sitting in plastic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make your own baby food and store it in reusable glass containers (bonus for budget, environment, and your baby’s health)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t want to make your own food, try to find baby food stored in glass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NEVER heat plastic in the microwave, use glass containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toys&quot;&gt;Toys:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I tried to avoid toys made of plastic, everything goes into their mouths. He loved his toys made of wood, silicone, and natural materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Babies grow quickly and outgrow toys – I made an effort to choose toys that wouldn’t leave an environmental impact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider buying second hand or getting hammy-downs as they get older and plastic toys are hard to avoid! We also had friends give us an exersaucer and swing, and our parents kept some of our own past favourite toys.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lil B is more than happy to play with my pots and pans, cardboard boxes, spoons, etc. and there are so many clever ideas on Pinterest for using things you already have around the house.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go outside – Lil B is enthralled with sticks, rocks, and leaves. We poke, pile, and sort them together. He learns new skills and about the wonderful world around him!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Children" /><summary type="html">Avoiding plastics is not only good for the environment, but also good for your health! While I realize one person avoiding single use plastic products won’t save the world, I am a firm believer that</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Tests Are Done For Thyroid Problems?</title><link href="https://drtaraburke.com/thyroid-testing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Tests Are Done For Thyroid Problems?" /><published>2019-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://drtaraburke.com/thyroid-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://drtaraburke.com/thyroid-testing/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-tests-are-done-for-thyroid-problems&quot;&gt;What Tests Are Done For Thyroid Problems?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, I get the question, “What labs should I have done to test my Thyroid?” In this blog post I will give you a good idea of where to start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thyroid-the-basics&quot;&gt;Thyroid: The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first, let’s talk a little about the Thyroid gland and its function in the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thyroid gland is a small butterfly shaped gland that sits at the base of your neck. It is a vitally important gland in your body and controls all things metabolism. Think of it like your internal thermostat – controlling temperature and weight as well as playing a role in menstrual cycles, mood, heart rate, breathing, digestion, and even cholesterol levels. Knowing all of this, it is clear why your Thyroid levels being even slightly off can lead to so many symptoms and make you feel terrible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Thyroid can either be working too hard, or not hard enough, with the former being called Hyperthyroid and the latter Hypothyroid. In addition, you can have an autoimmune disease which affects your Thyroid – called Hashimotos (which is a hypothyroid state) or Graves (which is a hyperthyroid state).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hormones-associated-with-the-thyroid&quot;&gt;Hormones Associated with the Thyroid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thyroid makes 2 main hormones, T3 and T4. T4 is converted to T3 outside of the Thyroid. T3 is considered the “active” hormone which controls the metabolism in almost every cell in your body!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you may be wondering what controls how much T3 and T4 your body makes. Your brain makes a hormone called TSH (Thyroid Stimulating Hormone), this hormone travels to your Thyroid, telling it to make MORE Thyroid hormones when it is HIGH and LESS Thyroid hormones when it is LOW. In hypothyroid your Thyroid hormones, T3 and T4, are low but your TSH is high- Think of it like your brain is YELLING at your Thyroid to make more hormones because there is not enough! (EDIT: Here is a recent video I did on this subject to help clear things up for you!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-start-with-lab-work&quot;&gt;Where to Start with Lab-Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a better understanding of your Thyroid let’s talk about what lab-work I usually run on my new patients who have Thyroid concerns or symptoms. Often TSH is solely run to assess thyroid function but I like to have a bit more information to help my patients feel optimal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TSH (Thyroid Stimulation Hormone)– Remember this is the signal from your brain to your thyroid, this number can tell me if your thyroid is working too hard or not hard enough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free T3 and Free T4– These are the hormones made by your thyroid, testing free hormones give me a better picture of your thyroid output&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thyroid Antibodies (to tell me if you have an autoimmune Thyroid disease like Graves or Hashimotos)
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thyroid peroxidase antibody (TPO)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thyroglobulin antibody (TGAb)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thyroid stimulating immunoglobulin (TSI)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-your-options&quot;&gt;Understanding Your Options:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These labs are a great starting point for telling me the health of your thyroid and where to start treatment! If you are interested in your thyroid function or have been diagnosed with a thyroid condition and would like in-depth testing and comprehensive treatment options I am here to help!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr. Tara Burke</name></author><category term="Naturopathic Medicine" /><category term="Thyroid" /><summary type="html">The Thyroid gland is a small butterfly shaped gland that sits at the base of your neck. It is a vitally important gland in your body and controls all things metabolism. Think of it like your internal thermostat</summary></entry></feed>